Chapter 104. The fossil whale.
From his mighty bulk the whale affords a most congenial theme whereon to enlarge,
amplify, and generally expatiate.
Would you? You could not compress him.
By good rights he should only be treated of in imperial folio. Not to tell over
again his furlongs from sphiracle to tail and the yards he measures about the
waist. Only think of the gigantic involutions of his intestines where they
lie in him like great cables and hawers coiled away in the subterranean orop
deck of a line of battleship.
Since I have undertaken to manhandle this Leviathan, it behooves me to
approve myself omnisiently exhaustive in the enterprise, not overlooking the
minutest seinal germs of his blood, and spinning him out to the uttermost coil
of his bowels. Having already described him in most of his present habitatory
and anatomical peculiarities, it now remains to magnify him in an archaeological fossilous and
anti-deluvian point of view. Applied to any other creature than the Leviathan,
to an ant or a flea, such portly terms might justly be deemed unwarrantably
grandiloquent. But when Leviathan is the text, the case is altered. Feain am I to
stagger to this imprise under the weightiest words of the dictionary. And
here be it said that whenever it has been convenient to consult one in the
course of these dissertations, I have invariably used a huge quarto edition of
Johnson expressly purchased for that purpose, because that famous
lexographers's uncommon personal bulk more than fitted him to compile a
lexicon to be used by a whale author like me.
One often hears of writers that rise and swell with their subject, though it may
seem but an ordinary one. How then, with me writing of this Leviathan,
unconsciously my chyography expands into placard capitals. Give me a condor's
quill. Give me Vuvius's crater for an inkstand. Friends, hold my arms. For in
the mere act of penning my thoughts of this Leviathan, they weary me and make
me faint with their outreaching comprehensiveness of sweep, as if to
include the whole circle of the sciences, and all the generations of
whales and men and mastadons, past, present, and to come, with all the
revolving panoramas of empire on Earth, and throughout the whole universe, not
excluding its suburbs. Such and so magnifying is the virtue of a large and
liberal theme. We expand to its bulk. To produce a mighty book, you must choose a
mighty theme. No great and enduring volume can ever be written on the flea,
though many there be who have tried it.
Heir entering upon the subject of fossil whales, I present my credentials as a
geologist, by stating that in my miscellaneous time I have been a
stonemason, and also a great digger of ditches, canals, and wells, wine vaults,
and sellers, and sistns of all sorts.
Likewise, by way of preliminary, I desire to remind the reader that while
in the earlier geological strata, there are found fossils of monsters now almost
completely extinct, these subsequent relics discovered in what are called the
tertiary formations seem the connecting or at any rate intercepted links between
the anti-chronical creatures and those whose remote posterity are said to have
entered the ark. All the fossil whales hitherto discovered belong to the
tertiary period which is the last preceding the superficial formations.
And though none of them precisely answer to any known species of the present
time, they are yet sufficiently akin to them in general respects to justify
their taking rank as citation fossils.
Detached broken fossils of pre-adamite whales, fragments of their bones and
skeletons, have within 30 years past at various intervals been found at the base
of the Alps, in Lombardi, in France, in England, in Scotland, and in the states
of Louisiana, Mississippi, and Alabama.
Among the more curious of such remains is part of a skull which in the year
1779 was disinterred in the ru doofan in Paris, a short street opening almost
directly upon the palace of the tuliaries and bones disinterred in
excavating the great docks of Antworp in Napoleon's time. Kouier pronounced these
fragments to have belonged to some utterly unknown Leviathanic species.
But by far the most wonderful of all citation relics was the almost complete
vast skeleton of an extinct monster found in the year 1842 on the plantation of Judge Cree in
Alabama. The awstricken credulous slaves in the vicinity took it for the bones of
one of the fallen angels. The Alabama doctors declared it a huge reptile and
bestowed upon it the name of Basilosaurus.
but some specimen bones of it being taken across the sea to Owen, the
English anatomist. It turned out that this alleged reptile was a whale, though
of a departed species. A significant illustration of the fact again and again
repeated in this book, that the skeleton of the whale furnishes but little clue
to the shape of his fully invested body.
So Owen recristened the monster Zugalodon and in his paper read before
the London Geological Society pronounced it in substance one of the most
extraordinary creatures which the mutations of the globe have blotted out of existence.
When I stand among these mighty Leviathan skeletons, skulls, tusks,
jaws, ribs, and vertebrae, all characterized by partial resemblances to
the existing breeds of sea monsters, but at the same time bearing, on the other
hand, similar affinities to the annihilated anti-chronical leviathans,
their incalculable seniors. I am by a flood born back to that wondrous period.
air time itself can be said to have begun, for time began with man. Here
Saturn's gray chaos rolls over me, and I obtain dim, shuddering glimpses into
those polar eternities, when wedged bastions of ice pressed hard upon what
are now the tropics, and in all the 25,000 mi of this world's circumference,
not an inhabitable hands breath of land was visible. Then the whole world was
the whales and king of creation. He left his wake along the present lines of the
Andes and the Himalayas. Who can show a pedigree like Leviathan? Ahab's harpoon
had shed older blood than the pharaohs.
Methuselah seems a school boy. I look round to shake hands with Shem. I am
horror struck at this anti-mosaic unsourced existence of the unspeakable
terrors of the whale, which having been before all time, must needs exist after
all humane ages are over.
But not alone has this Leviathan left his pre-adamite traces in the stereotype
plates of nature and in limestone and marl bequed his ancient bust. But upon
Egyptian tablets whose antiquity seems to claim for them an almost
fossiliferous character, we find the unmistakable print of his fin. In an
apartment of the great temple of Dendara some 50 years ago, there was discovered
upon the granite ceiling a sculptured and painted planosphere abounding in
centaurs, griffins, and dolphins, similar to the grotesque figures on the
celestial globe of the moderns. Gliding among them, old Leviathans swam as of
Yore, was there swimming in that planosphere centuries before Solomon was cradled.
Nor must there be omitted another strange attistation of the antiquity of
the whale in his own ass postivvian reality as set down by the venerable
John Leo the old barber traveler. Quote, "Not far from the seaside they have a
temple, the rafters and beams of which are made of whale bones, for whales of a
monstrous size are often times cast up dead upon that shore. The common people
imagine that by a secret power bestowed by God upon the temple, no whale can
pass it without immediate death. But the truth of the matter is that on either
side of the temple there are rocks that shoot two miles into the sea and wound
the whales when they light upon him.
They keep a whale's rib of an incredible length for a miracle, which lying upon
the ground with its convex part uppermost, makes an arch, the head of
which cannot be reached by a man upon a camels back. This rib, says John
Leo, is said to have lain there a hundred years before I saw it. Their
historians affirm that a prophet who prophesied of Muhammad came from this
temple. And some do not stand to assert that the prophet Jonas was cast forth by
the whale at the base of the temple. End quote.
In this Africle of the whale I leave you, reader, and if you be a nantucketer
and a whaleman, you will silently worship there.